<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some further remarks upon Mr. Gadbury's defence of Scorpio by way of addition, to a just reward for unreasonable service. Wherein not only Mr. Gadbury's pretentions to astrology are dissipated; but even his title to learning and right reason (which by virtue of his horoscope he challenges) is shaken. By the Man in the Moon.</title>
            <author>Lilly, William, 1602-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48516</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828441</idno>
  <idno type="VID">32868</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240862515</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216719</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828441</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99828441e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48516)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32868)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1913:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some further remarks upon Mr. Gadbury's defence of Scorpio by way of addition, to a just reward for unreasonable service. Wherein not only Mr. Gadbury's pretentions to astrology are dissipated; but even his title to learning and right reason (which by virtue of his horoscope he challenges) is shaken. By the Man in the Moon.</title>
                  <author>Lilly, William, 1602-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year MDCLXXVI. [1676]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Man in the Moon = William Lilly. Attribution from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Gadbury, John, 1627-1704 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32868:1"/>
            <p>SOME Further Remarks Upon Mr. GADBURY's DEFENCE of SCORPIO, By way of addition, to a just Reward for unreasonable service.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN Not only Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi>'s Pretensions to Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy are dissipated; but even his Title <hi>to Learning and right Reason</hi> (which by virtue of his Horoscope he challenges) is shaken.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Man in the Moon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Bilem saepe jocum vestri movere tumultus.</q>
            <p>Printed in the Year MDCLXXVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:32868:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32868:2"/>
            <head>To the Worshipful Mr. JOHN GADBURY, <hi>Quondam Taylor</hi> in Ordinary to Mr. <hi>William Lilly;</hi> now Extraordinary Physician to Her Majesty, and a <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretis</hi> to the Peerless <hi>Dulcinea,</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise called the <hi>Gardiner</hi>'s Daughter.</head>
            <p>IT was well observed by one (a Philosopher no doubt, and I am very sorry I have not a Greek Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegm to express it by, for the honour of you my learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Patron) that when a Dog, though of never so great valour and courage, happens by the chance of
<pb facs="tcp:32868:3"/> War to be worried, every whiffling Cur, that before durst scarcely lift his leg before him to piss, will be sure to have a snap at him. But still would I have you comfort your self with your own doctrine.</p>
            <q>
               <l>But Rats in Science, least things ever chuse</l>
               <l>To nibble at; that's the base Vermins use.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And though your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies rejoyce, and <hi>Scorpio</hi> be found to be a very lewd Sign, yet keep as long as you can on this side Hell (as 'tis canted) and exercise nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:32868:3"/> Knife, Halter, nor Pill. The Lady <hi>Dulcinea</hi> is still <hi>in effe,</hi> young &amp; kind, and there may come a time, when you may have <hi>45. l.</hi> for your five sheets again, be but humble and faithful, and leave off this habit of writing scurrilous non-sence, and I dare engage, you shall conciliate the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of all Mankind, as much as of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Servant,</hi> The Man in the Moon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:32868:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS many of you as have read, the <hi>Just Reward for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable Service,</hi> will conclude that my Attempt is but <hi>Actum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere;</hi> and I do but dance after the Pipe of the Author of those smart Annotations: I confess he hath display'd the most principal absurdities of our Blundering A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strologer, yet are there some Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial ones, which he hath omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which you will find in the following Pages. I must acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge too, had not that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb facs="tcp:32868:4"/> written, you had never seen any production of this nature of mine: For till I by accident saw his reflexions, I had never heard <hi>John Gadbury</hi>'s defence of Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio (whence you may conclude that I lived in a Garret too) but observing so much Salt in them, and the great advantage which he had over his Antagonist, I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined that <hi>John Gadbury</hi>'s Book could not but be very pleasant; so that presently I procured it, and having perused it, being a little idly disposed, resolved to divert my self and you, with what had not been already ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served; and if you compare this with the first Annotations, you will find, that I am no Plagiary;
<pb facs="tcp:32868:5"/> And though you find, the <hi>Man in the Moon</hi> in the Title-page, yet am I neither Animal <hi>Cornu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> nor so Lunatick as a Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pionist, that (like a Moon-shiny night) barks at his own shadow.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare-well.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32868:5"/>
            <p>HAd Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi>'s Annotator de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signed to have dealt impartially, and (as he pretends) like an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byass'd Person, he would never so severely have examined the extravagancies of a Man, so long time reputed <hi>non compos men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis;</hi> nor ought he to have taken notice of his inconsistencies and contradictions, in a Book that was scribled in a <hi>delirious fit;</hi> but have cited his opinion of the influence of the Stars, before they had so unhappily exerted it upon his brain, <hi>i. e.</hi> before he was quite infatuated, and turned Mad-man: for in his Preface to his <hi>Coll. Gen.</hi> (particularly that Part that is borrowed from Sir <hi>Chr. Heydon nomine sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presso</hi>) he tells us, <hi>That the Stars do so strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encline, that the effects of Nature are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly seen beyond the force of education.</hi> Nay, within these seven years <hi>it pleased God to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Stars with such Energy</hi> (which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive consists not with <hi>gently inclining) that among five thousand Nativities, he can with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence assert, they have never been found to fail,</hi> see Prognost. for 1669. Might not the Title of <hi>Silly Sophister</hi> have been as justly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:32868:6"/> to him by his Annotator, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the Heirs of Hell from being any part of Gods Creation, because they have no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to Heaven, as for endeavouring to prove by a Negative? With what face can J. G. object to Mr. L. his stigmatizing Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio, when in the gross he so irreverently transfers the particulars of the change on <hi>Sampson?</hi> But to come more closely, <hi>Really, Gentlemen, I must tell ye, if ye did believe Mr.</hi> Lilly <hi>in his black charge to be true, you ought to anticipate his malice; take courage and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come your own Butchers, for certainly Persons of his character, as he saith ye all are for being born under Scorpio, can but faintly hope for any share in Heaven at last, and then to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose should we, that are born under so dismal an Ascendant, covet to live?</hi> Senceless Sot! but argued like the Author.</p>
            <p>Might not our Annotator have observed (had he been unbiass'd) that these words do most apparently convict our Astrologer, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Heresie, or folly and stupidity? I confess I am willing to put the safest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction upon it, and for once admit it to proceed out of his abundant simplicity, and only tell him that he argues like a most egre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Ass: For if he believes a future punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by the misfortune of his Horos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope is incapacitated for pretending any share
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:32868:6"/> in Heaven, it is stupendious folly to accele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate those inexpressible torments that afflict the damned, by cutting his own throat.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato (as quoted by Plutarch) maketh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence superiour to Necessity or Destiny; Mr.</hi> L. <hi>if he allow Providence at all, placeth it below them.</hi> But why should J. G. transfer this confounded non-sense upon Mr. L. when it had its conception of his own <hi>Addle-pate?</hi> For I would fain be satisfied, how Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence can be imagined by any rational Man, if there be a necessity in the disposition of humane affairs? though I doubt not, but our Author can reconcile Fate and Providence as easily, as the hooks and eyes of a Suit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> L. <hi>must pardon me, I cannot help it,</hi> &amp;c. This is the mighty Advocate for free-will, he that would exclude all coercion upon the mind of Man, cannot now help his differing in opinion from Mr. L. and how should a Man, in whom non-sence and repugnancies are inherent, avoid contradicting himself, and writing like an Ass?</p>
            <p>I cannot but commend his prudence (or rather subtility, for you know his Horos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope) in waving those disputes, which God knows he is no more able to manage or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine than his <hi>quondam</hi> Goose notions, which at second or third hand he hath glean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, and here shuffling in by the head and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32868:7"/> shoulders, by his hints would be thought a Philosopher. I cannot but laugh at his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet of <hi>prodigious</hi> for Scorpio, there being such a prodigy of Astrology, and an <hi>olio</hi> of Saints spawned under it, <hi>for you may observe, good Reader, Scorpionists spawn apace.</hi> I would desire our Author to tell me by what figure of non-sence he terms that immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, <hi>which is no longer liv'd than the carkess.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>L.</hi> (it seems) in his Almanack for 1673. hath a little severely reflected upon Scorpio, and Persons born under it: <hi>Gadbury</hi> in recapitulating the affront, doth not only exert his resentment, but very wittily (as he thinks) upbraids him with tautology; But would not a wise Man have taken care, that he had been secure before he had recrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated? But to prove this Coxcomb's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence by right of birth equivalent to Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi>'s, pray read in the very page where he makes this observation, and you shall find, <hi>This Mundane frame or fabrick is of so excellent a texture and composure, and is so choice and exquisite a piece of clock-work, so glorious and orderly as well in each particular, as in its ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral motion, that should the least pin or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle thereof be wanting or amiss, or indeed in any other nature or temper, shape or condition, or in any other order than it is, the whole World would run to ruine or destruction.</hi> If ever such
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32868:7"/> an hideous piece of bombast (for bombast, if for once you will admit a clench, hath formerly been as essential to his profession as filching) was read before in a Fellow, that pretended to reprove tautology in another, I will be bound to read the non-sence of this Author as long as I live, and I think my life would then be as uncomfortable as a Scorpio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists, were Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi>'s charge true.</p>
            <p>As it is our Author's endeavour in all his writings, to illustrate and adorn (as he thinks) his discourses with hard words, so hath he no small affectation to lard them with Greek and Latin Verses: His skill in the Greek is unquestionably as eminent as Sir <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibras</hi>'s, and for Latin he hath as much I dare swear as the Geese that preserved the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol; for an instance take these two (Verses I cannot call them) as they lye p. 5.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Cunctis inest canibus pro consuetudine natum,</l>
               <l>Ʋt latrave magis quam feritare solent.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Here hath our Author outdone the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, killed three Birds with one stone, given us a <hi>specimen</hi> of his skill in the Latin, of his Poetick vein, and lastly girded his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagonist; but would any but our egregiously stupid Fop, have thus shamefully betrayed his own ignorance? Can he think Men such
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32868:8"/> Sots, as to believe that he who would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose such stuff to the publick, could have any understanding (as he pretends) in the learned Languages? <hi>Seneca,</hi> I remember, hath an expression that runs thus: <hi>Quibusdam ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus sic innatum est, ut non pro feritate sed pro consuetudine latrent.</hi> But because I am sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible he is ignorant enough, not to apprehend the absurdities of his own without some inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, I will desire him to scan the first line, then construe it and tell of what use <hi>natum</hi> is, and where he meets with the Verb <hi>feritare,</hi> except in his own barbarous Poetry? Yet to convince you further of his skill in the Latin, hath he not in his <hi>Doctr. Nat.</hi> pag. 137. put Woman in breeches, and made her of the Masculin gender, <hi>moriturus ante natum?</hi> what think you of <hi>applicat. ad</hi> □☿ <hi>Dominus nonae?</hi> hath not he (to prove his acquaintance with the Poets) discovered <hi>Seneca</hi> to be but a plagiary, and stole that Chorus <hi>Fatis agimur?</hi> &amp;c. which we find in his <hi>Oedipus,</hi> from <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian;</hi> as very gravely he cites him for the Author of it, in his Title-page to the Nativity of King <hi>Charles</hi> Astrologically handled. His Annotator has (I think) sufficiently lashed him for his challenge, to produce one Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor that hath stigmatized Scorpio. But, saith <hi>John,</hi> if such Authors there be, <hi>they and Mr. Lilly stand in eminent need of Heaven's
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32868:8"/> Amnestia.</hi> But, Friend <hi>John,</hi> have the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens a greater respect for Scorpio, than any other Sign of the Zodiack? Or may you alone securely cast what imputations you please upon the Celestial Bodies? For if I mistake not, you charge the Planets ill digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, (<hi>Vide Doctr. Nat.</hi> pag. 67, 68, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) as scandalously as Mr. <hi>L.</hi> doth Scorpio.</p>
            <p>Your Annotator hath very justly acquitted Mr. <hi>L.</hi> from your scandal, of believing the Stars to be essentially evil, and impellent causes: But how you will purge your self, I cannot conceive; for by as much as may be collected from expression, I am satisfied that you did believe them to be cogent (however you have now changed that note) when you wrote these words: If <hi>Venus be found in Libra or Taurus, whatsoever the nativity be, the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive shall affect lewd Women, and he shall be a Fornicator. Doctr. Nat.</hi> pag. 80.</p>
            <p>And what construction will the subsequent words admit: <hi>And I am perswaded; that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever have</hi> ♂ <hi>and</hi> ♀ <hi>in their nativities</hi> (as of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity all Persons have) <hi>will be more or less (according to their dignities therein) concerned in the question: that is, they will by an innate Impulse, do that which is much worse, Vide Doct. Nat.</hi> p. 130. And now whether these words do not imply a coercion, contrary to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which he here maintains, I appeal to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32868:9"/> any Scorpionist in <hi>Europe.</hi> But whether by <hi>much worse</hi> he means fornication, or <hi>Istud quod digitis Gadbury perdis homo est,</hi> I cannot determine, but it may be both.</p>
            <p>Now for the particular branches of the charge, and the first that occurs is <hi>falsity,</hi> and (quoth <hi>John) That is the counterfeit of verity according to the etymon, such an one as breaks open Letters,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>if it be wickedness to conceal the fault of that which a man selleth, surely open, publick and professed falshood is wickedness with a witness.</hi> Besides the non-sence and tauto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy here, you may observe that according to the etymon (as he absurdly calls it) falsity is the counterfeit of verity, <hi>i. e.</hi> either it hath some resemblance to verity; That essentially there is between them, is obvious: and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the other sence, it is a flat repugnance <hi>to open publick,</hi> &amp;c. So that you see here is non-sence with a witness; thus doth this stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid disputant blunder in his first particular.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Arrogance, and there he tells us out of <hi>Solomon: There is more hopes of a fool, than of one that is wise in his own conceit, and subjoyns that 'tis the greatest enemy to prudence that can be.</hi> From whence I collect that this <hi>J. Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> is like to be a fool to the end of the play: For, saith <hi>Solomon, There is no hope of him.</hi> But this learned Author can't be content to quote a Wise Man, but he must make him break poor <hi>Priscian</hi>'s head.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32868:9"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Ambition is the mother of Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition;</hi> and yet (quoth he) <hi>vain glory</hi> (which with him <hi>idem sonat) ends in lewdness, so that to be ambitious is to live vitiously:</hi> How these cohere I apprehend not, nor it may be the only wise and learned <hi>J. Gadbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Ingratitude,</hi> and of this was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any Scorpionist guilty; I only desire him to reflect upon himself, and what excuse he can frame, let him know according to his own maxime, <hi>Knavery in one person, is no excuse for ingratitude in another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Boasting, which is a vice</hi> (saith <hi>John) opposed to valour;</hi> which by his favour is no consequent, there being so frequent examples of their compatibility. It is wonderful to him, <hi>how boasting falls to the share of a Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pionist, since Scorpio is the House of Mars, and Mars the author of true courage;</hi> and this you have in general, be <hi>Mars</hi> well or ill dignified: <hi>So that a pratler</hi> (which is consisting enough with boasting) <hi>without modesty or honesty, a Broacher of quarrels, a Thief, a perjured or turbulent Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, a Promoter of mischiefs, a rash inhumane treacherous Fellow, a meer Incendiary, one that neither Years God, neither cares for honouring or revering Man,</hi> (which is his own character of <hi>Mars</hi> ill dignified) and such a <hi>Mars</hi> as himself was born under, may have as just a pretence to true valour as any, and if so, I see no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32868:10"/> for the exclusion of the Boaster.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, <hi>Lying;</hi> and here Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> hath hit it: and <hi>John,</hi> notwithstanding all the Authors which so learnedly thou enumeratest, thou wilt never be able to acquit thy self from this stigma; for certainly thou (if any Man) art according to thy own pretty Phrase, the very <hi>Coloquintida of conversation.</hi> A <hi>Thief</hi> (saith <hi>John) is better than a Lyar.</hi> We have indeed a Proverb that saith, <hi>He that will lye will steal;</hi> and no man doubts, but he that will steal will lye: That <hi>John</hi> will steal, I can prove by his plagiarism; that he will lye, by his words.</p>
            <p>I could not choose but laugh, when I saw <hi>lechery</hi> in the seventh place, and <hi>John Gadbury</hi> at the beginning; but his learned Annotator (though no Church-warden) hath brought home the brat to his door again, though like an unnatural Father he had renounced it, and exposed it to the mercy of the Parish. Yet ought the Annotator not to have been so se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, but to have considered that besides the provocations of the flesh, there was a mighty sympathy in their Nativities; and that though the Stars are no <hi>impellent causes,</hi> yet sometimes they incline very strongly. In the mean time let Mr. <hi>G.</hi> tell me, whether in all his Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical reading he never met an Author that (speaking of a Scorpionist) saith, <hi>Erit talis
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32868:10"/> qui semper advenereos coitus oculorum cupiditate cogatur?</hi> And doth he not remember that his Friend <hi>Firmicus</hi> tells him, that <hi>Lollianus</hi> his own Patron, <hi>Ob crimen adulterii in exilium da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus est?</hi> yet this <hi>Lollianus</hi> was a Scorpionist too.</p>
            <p>Eightly, <hi>Perjury;</hi> I cannot blame Mr. <hi>Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> for being a little on the huff in this para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph; yet to qualify him a little, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his peremptory character of <hi>Mars</hi> ill dignified; but what then? I can take a box on the ear with less regret from my self, than from the best Astrologer in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ninthly and lastly, comes <hi>Revenge;</hi> and he assures us that Mr. <hi>L.</hi> hath tryed, <hi>Whether the Scorpionists are Pigeon-liver'd, or have any such commodity as revenge; and that he hath rendered Heaven</hi> (for I suppose he means no more by that enthusiastical tautology, of the <hi>most holy Seat of the most holy and tremend God, the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the blessed Angels, the resting place of the Faithful, the Church of the Elect) a place of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and blackness, a Desart of destruction, a Source, a Sink, a Seed-plot of all terrene unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piness.</hi> Now how prettily these fulsome Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors cohere, let any Man of sense judge; but it was the zeal, the abundant zeal of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxitated Author, that belch'd out this absurd bombast.</p>
            <p>I concur with him, that it is very rare <hi>to find a Fool born under Scorpio;</hi> yet I neither
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32868:11"/> speak treason, nor contradict my self, if I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm I know several Cockscombs, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly one egregious Fop, by name <hi>John Gadbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again (quoth <hi>John) If Scorpio were a Sign so bad,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>how comes it to pass that neither the learned Cardan, nor the ingenious Morinus say not one word thereof?</hi> Although the Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor had not the happiness to recollect <hi>Cardan</hi>'s and <hi>Morine</hi>'s testimonies (for who can retain every expression in so many hundred Pages?) yet will it be no affront to him, to observe the transcendent impudence and ignorance of this pretending Astrologian? This is the Man that would be thought to have read <hi>Cardan</hi> and <hi>Morine</hi> so accuratly, that no expression hath escaped him, or else he sawcily concludes all Men as ignorant as himself; and because he never read them (at least to no purpose, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver understood them) no Man hath. But to demonstrate his ignorance to his indelible shame, let him read <hi>Card. Aph.</hi> 55. <hi>Segm.</hi> 2. and he shall find, that <hi>Compositos &amp; pulchros Aries facit, Scorpius mendaces,</hi> and there I think is one word for him. Again <hi>Aph.</hi> 166. <hi>Segm.</hi> 5. <hi>Aquea signa faciunt proditores atque in his Scorpius excellit,</hi> there is another. I will not insist upon <hi>Aph.</hi> 140. <hi>Segm.</hi> 2. <hi>Mercurius ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xime hebetatur in signis humidis, sed in Scorpione facit maleficum.</hi> Nor had I cared if he had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32868:11"/>
               <hi>Scorpius solicitudinem animi (intellige denotat) &amp; deceptionem,</hi> because <hi>Morine</hi> comes to my assistance, pag. 462. Astr. Gall. <hi>Quibus ascendit Scorpio hi sicut timidiores, prudentiores, ad dissimulandum aptiores, &amp; clam insidias iram suam explevit ultionibus.</hi> Here is hypocrisie, treachery, revenge and anger; and what will an angry, treacherous hypocrite, that studies revenge, boggle at or not attempt? But <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi> hath not yet done, for p. 504. disputing, whether the Celestial Bodies are only universal causes, he hath these words: <hi>At prout effectui, hoc est, homini vel equo genito particulares con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert qualitates, qu as nec homo, nec equus conferunt quod nempe sint a propria signi influentia, ut ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligni mores a Scorpione in ascendente.</hi> For the true understanding the question debated by <hi>Morine,</hi> let <hi>Cap.</hi> 6, <hi>lib.</hi> 21. be consulted; what I have here transcribed, is sufficient to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate Mr. <hi>G.</hi> an huffing ignorant preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. He can't be to seek in the signification of <hi>maligni est,</hi> as his Annotator wittily observes, he knows most words in <hi>Rider</hi> &amp; <hi>Thomas</hi> too: Yet believing, he may be as perfect in them as in <hi>Morine</hi> and <hi>Cardan,</hi> I would advise him to betake himself to one of them; and I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, he will find no one word that doth more significantly express, or fully compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the whole charge, drawn up by Mr. <hi>L.</hi> against Scorpio, than <hi>maligni</hi> doth.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:32868:12"/>
            <p>But how could Mr. <hi>G.</hi> were he not a Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pionist, upbraid Mother <hi>Shipton,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Sybils?</hi> with what face can he so wittily (as he thinks) joke upon him, as if he could produce none but Astrologers of his own begetting, to te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stify to his charge?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haly, an eminent Arabian Astrologer, is pleased to terme Scorpio an humble and depressed Sign. How Mr. Haly, an humble and depressed Sign, and yet guilty of perjury, lying?</hi> &amp;c. Yes, Mr. <hi>G.</hi> he is pleased to do so, and at the same time he terms it <hi>deceptor</hi> too; but like a true Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pionist you take occasion to leave out that. But, upon these words of <hi>Haly,</hi> he endeavours to prove ♏ an obedient Sign, and obedience a passive quality; and then brings in <hi>Johannes Angelus</hi> and <hi>Firmicus,</hi> to testify that it denotes the Native to be <hi>iracundos &amp; agiles;</hi> but how <hi>humilitas</hi> and <hi>iracundia</hi> do consist, I do not conceive.</p>
            <p>Our Author need not to have taken such pains, to have enumerated such an heap of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorisms, to prove the influence of ♂ (as we know it) destructive and pernicious. Nor do I conceive that, because ♂ is a Planet of a malevolent influence, ♏ is an innocent Sign; and that because those Authors, which he cites, do condemn ♂ his heats, they therefore acquit ♏ from all intemperance. Nor do I care whether ♏, as the House of ♂ or from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32868:12"/> any innate vicious quality, does inflict such vices into the Native; yet we know <hi>aliud ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficit</hi> ♂ <hi>in</hi> ♈, <hi>aliud in</hi> ♏. But let it suffice, that for any thing alledged by our Friend <hi>John,</hi> Scorpionists may be as profligate Raskals, as for <hi>John</hi>'s, and the sake of some others, we have reason to suspect they are. But for the operation of the Signs, either <hi>dependenter a Plaueta,</hi> or <hi>per se, Vide Morinam c.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guido Bonatus</hi> (it seems) had observed Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pionists (as I have) to be very great Lyars; and therefore says, that a Person born under ♏ shall be one <hi>In cujus ore vix aut nunquam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venietur veritas.</hi> But, saith Mr. <hi>G.</hi> he can be no more true in this than he that said, <hi>In his hast all men were Lyars;</hi> which is a modest way of giving King <hi>David</hi> the lye: But <hi>Guido</hi> contradicts himself, and therefore no way serviceable to Mr. <hi>L.</hi> saith Mr. <hi>G.</hi> but if <hi>Guido</hi>'s repugnancies do invalidate his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, than I do pronounce this whole Book of Mr. <hi>G.</hi> in defence of ♏ <hi>ipso facto</hi> null and void, being repleat with nothing but flat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, as I think his Annotator hath proved to his indelible shame.</p>
            <p>I cannot but laugh at that high-strained piece of experimental Philosophy (as 'tis phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed) so much applauded by <hi>John,</hi> viz. <hi>Campa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nella</hi>'s putting himself into a distorted po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture, when he was writing to a crooked Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32868:13"/> he ought to have put on his Robes too, and in every thing else as near as he could have personated one of that function, and then I believe his fancy might have operated as effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually, as if he had written in his natural po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sture. I am resolved, if ever I should have oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion to make use of Mr. <hi>G.</hi> I will (as near as I can) put my self into the shape of a Hog, and represent <hi>Epicuri degrege Porcum;</hi> nay, I will imagine Scorpio to be my Ascendant, and then assume my pen, and try <hi>to meet his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour in the thing I write about.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean time, I am glad there is so compendious a method discovered, for the reconcilement of differences: Put your selves into the frame of your Adversary, send him a Letter; and, quoth <hi>John,</hi> there is <hi>a Period of the contention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our accurate Astrologer (like an insensible Blunderer) is again at Mr. <hi>L.</hi> for contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself, but it is endless harping upon that string: Only let me ask him, what he will prove by producing his twenty genitures? for when all comes to all, he tells you he will prove; but, what? go look, and prudently he evades that; for I see nothing he is like to prove, but himself an Ass.</p>
            <p>He is not only offended at Mr. <hi>L.</hi> for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Natives of ♏; but all Persons that inhabited that part of the Earth, to whom ♏
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32868:13"/> ascended at the Suns entrance into ♈. Yet you shall hear this perfidious Scorpionist him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self speak upon the very same occasion. <hi>If</hi> ♏ <hi>be a Sign of falsity, as Hermes in the</hi> 9th. <hi>Aph. of his Cent. affirms it to be, then we may be glad, it is so nearly of the Horoscope at the time of this vernal ingress,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>a little after; this part of it is the decanate of</hi> ♀, <hi>&amp; habet significationem ebrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis bellorum &amp; fornicationis, to all which kinds of evils and debauchery men will much incline,</hi> &amp;c. [See his Judgment upon the year 1669.] With what brow then can this fulsome Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger call Mr. <hi>L. Impostor,</hi> and transfer all those Epithets upon him, which Scorpio doth so naturally challenge for its Natives? But, I think, I may as justly (without any viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of truth or breach of good manners) pronounce this <hi>J. G.</hi> an illiterate trifling Scribler, and a bungling Astrologian: the first I have already proved, and the last too in part; but more fully to confirm both, I will examine his twenty examples, at least what hath been by his learned Annotator omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: And the first that occurs is King <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. of <hi>England;</hi> and it is pity we have him not under the title of Monarch of <hi>Great Brittain,</hi> as (like an Owl) he gives us <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in his <hi>Coll. of Genit.</hi> But what will he prove by his Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity? Why, that he was a valiant Prince. Who
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32868:14"/> denyes it? But will he prove that Mrs. <hi>Alice Pierce</hi> and he, were no more contemporaries than <hi>Dido</hi> &amp; <hi>Aeneas?</hi> Or can he justify the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the Earl of <hi>Kent?</hi> But perhaps our Author may reply, the first of these was occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sioned by the ☌ of ♂ and ♀. But what then? <hi>All things are subordinate to the Horoscope.</hi> Were that then a sign of that vertue and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, which he would have us believe, it <hi>might have overborn that single testimony.</hi> Seeing therefore the matter of fact is true, it must be attributed to his Horoscope, according to our Author, who (like a wise Astrologer, but more zealous Scorpionist) tells us, that there is <hi>nothing in this Nativity, but the Horoscope to recommend it to the World:</hi> For, saith he, ♂ <hi>Lord of the Ascendant therein combust, in</hi> ☍ <hi>to</hi> ♃ <hi>and</hi> ☌ <hi>with</hi> ♀ <hi>Lady of the</hi> 7th. But did ever any Fellow argue thus against himself? For what could be desired greater for a Prince, whose design and glory it was to be victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, than to have the Lord of the Ascen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant strong therein, disposing of his Enemies (as ♂ doth of ♀) in ☌ with the Lord of the M. C.? and he must give me leave to tell him, that it is the opinion of some more learned than himself, that an ☍ of ♃ and ♂ makes men successful in War: and of this (were it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary) I could produce many instances. But if the grandeur of this Native be, to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32868:14"/> solely to his Horoscope; why is not that of every Scorpionist? or why is not every Scorpionist as eminent (<hi>quoad capax,</hi> as Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers cant) as this Native, and as worthy.</p>
            <p>The Electour of <hi>Saxony</hi> is (by the Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor) very pertinently charged with ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and consequently with the whole indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for <hi>ingratum si dixeris omnia dixeris:</hi> Yet this Electour was a <hi>freeholder of Reason</hi> as well as of his Electourship, and though there was an Antipathy betwixt the Emperour's Nativity and his, yet his reason (one would have thought might have exterminated his vices. But (saith he) <hi>their ambition and particular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs might differ:</hi> observe this conjuring dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putant! he undertakes to acquit all Scorpio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists from the black charge of Mr. <hi>L.</hi> and here makes no more, but point blank confounds his design, confutes himself, and very wisely charges this Prince (brought by him to give a testimony against Mr. <hi>L.</hi>) with <hi>ambition</hi> a particular branch of the Charge.</p>
            <p>I shall observe nothing in the 6th example, but Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi>'s Epiphonema, <hi>viz. Kings and Princes are Mr.</hi> Lilly<hi>'s tennis balls as well as the Stars, and must be toss'd and struck up and down as he is pleased, to bandy them with his black and envious racket.</hi> Here's a Metaphorical piece of non-sence for you, and is scarcely so good as if he had said, I am a wooden Astro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32868:15"/> made of flesh and bone, and so speak non-sence very elegantly with my pen.</p>
            <p>I have too great a veneration for the Royal Family to make any ill reflections (were I able) upon the seventh example; yet can I not omit Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi>'s praevarication, for first he publishes this Lady's Nativity (in that Book where he pretends to exhibit all the genitures of the most illustrious Branches of that Family) and makes ♏ 22. ascend. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards in his <hi>Coll. Gen.</hi> he is ashamed of that Horoscope, and therefore recants, and tells us that the proceeding was erroneous, and that <hi>sine dubio,</hi> that which he there presents us with, is the true one; and in that he places ♎ 27. ascending, and very pertinently gives the Ascendant <hi>ad</hi> □ ♂ for the small Pox, of which she expired. Here again like a false and subtile Scorpionist, he would perswade us that ♏ 1, 52. did ascend; But what credit is to be given to a Fellow that shall print a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity three times variously, especially when it may rationally be presumed, that this alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is only to accommodate it to his idle purpose? but admitting this to be true, I demand what the Ascendant <hi>ad</hi> □ ♂ gave her about 23? I hope a Direction, which he makes fatal if ♎ ascend, shall not pass without ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect when ♏ is in the Horoscope: But find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this inconsistency in him, this example
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32868:15"/> can prevail nothing with the Reader to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile him to ♏, when there is greater probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity that ♎ was Horoscopical.</p>
            <p>I do not conceive that this row of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, which this Trifler produces, do at all contribute to the redemption of his own or Scorpio's credit: For first, he borrows them all from the most uncorrected collection (abate but his own) of one of the most negligent Authors (<hi>J. G.</hi> alwayes excepted) that ever wrote: But then admitting the figures to be true, what he can collect from the words of <hi>Argol.</hi> I apprehend not, he having only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to give an account of critical dayes, it being eccentrick from his purpose to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion any thing of their merits. But Mr. <hi>Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> esteems it no small indication of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert of the first and second Cardinal, whose Nativities he produces, that they had the favour of so great a Man as Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the Eighth, <hi>Who know well enough how to make choice of Ministers for the Churches Peace and happiness,</hi> saith our Author. Yet you shall hear his opinion of this very Pope, in his Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servations upon his Nativity in his <hi>Collect. Gen.</hi> pag. 79. <hi>If this be this Pope's true Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity (as Argol avers) it seems to me that he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Papal dignity more by Policy than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, and was made the Head of the Church more for necessity than for any Religion.</hi> So that what
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32868:16"/> instruments a Pope that had neither desert nor Religion, was like to make choice of, let any Man judge.</p>
            <p>The tenth, is a Cardinal with a long name, that flourished under Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the Fifth, <hi>and received according to his worth and merit favours from him: So that you see Scorpio, or Persons born under it, are not so notoriously wicked,</hi> &amp;c. You may observe that Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi> in all these examples, makes them to have attained their preferments by their merits. But hear him in his calculation of his own Nativity, in his <hi>Doctr. Nat. Seriously protesting that the great reason, why he hath no more honour and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (and what could a nitty Astrologer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect or deserve?) <hi>according to the best of his judgment is, because he hath alwayes detested and hated the art of flattery and dissimulation, the ONELY Stairs by which ALL Persons ascend to honour and preferment.</hi> So that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the best of his judgment, All these Persons whom he so descants, attained their preferments by no other means but flattery and dissimulation: Thus doth <hi>Jack Gadbury</hi> sawcily contradict the Astrologer, and makes no more of proving him an Ass, than if he still lived by the Goose.</p>
            <p>In the Nativity of Dr. <hi>Gell</hi> I shall only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the position of ♄ <hi>in</hi> ♌ in the 9th: and quote that Aphorism, which he accommodates
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32868:16"/> to Pope <hi>Clement the Eigth,</hi> ♄ <hi>in the ninth House ill dignified, denotes an hypocrite or dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembler: makes him heretical and guilty of great errours in matters of Faith and Religion</hi> What can be from hence concluded, but Mr. <hi>Gad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> is an hair-brain'd, hot-headed Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian, giving his judgment as the toy takes him, or prejudice or favour sway him, and not from any sober and regulated principles of Art.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Regiomontanus</hi> is the twelfth, and seeing Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi> hath taken occasion to dignify him with the titles of learned, judicious, and ingenious, and with <hi>Origanus</hi> stile him <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theseos ocellus,</hi> hear <hi>Cardan</hi> of him: <hi>Monte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regius multa sibi ex aliorum laboribus ascripse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Tabulae Directionum magna ex parte sunt ipsius</hi> Joannis de Bianchinus <hi>Ital. extant apud me locupletiores, illas Monteregium vidisse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stat cum de aspectibus loquitur, epitoma est Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diolanensis cujusdam antequam etiam Purbachius Monteregii magister nasceretur, liber de trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis Sphaericis inventio tota est Hebri Hispani: Ephemerides inventae sunt antequam nasceretur, habui enim Ephemeridem anni</hi> 1412. So that you see <hi>Cardan</hi> hath almost put out this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical eye, and <hi>Regiomontanus</hi> being thus <hi>furtivis nudatus coloribus,</hi> appears like a true Scorpionist. For, saith Mr. <hi>Gadbury, It is as horrid a crime to steal the labours of the dead, as to rob the houses of the living.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:32868:17"/>
            <p>For the account we have of <hi>Ramzovius,</hi> we are chiefly obliged to his own self, and a few parasitical Poetasters: But from his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting I do pronounce him a vain-glorious Ass, and a boasting Astrologer. As any Man will be convinced, that will view his <hi>Tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Astrologicus, &amp; de Annis Climacterieis,</hi> at the end of both, which Books you may find not only a medly of other mens <hi>Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantry,</hi> subjoyned purely for ostentation, but his own vain account of his extraction; which is a thing so childish and ridiculous that a Wise man would blush at it. However, boasting is a branch of Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi>'s charge, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which this Person comes, so that this nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity is impertinent as any of the other, and proves nothing in defence of ♏.</p>
            <p>Then for <hi>Angelus Politianus</hi> (whose Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty follows) he did onely (as your Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Mr. <hi>Gadbury,</hi> observes) say that he never spent his time worse than when he read the Bible, but that reading Saint <hi>Hierom</hi>'s tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slation, it had made him forget to write good Latin; but in defence of his poysoning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, it may be alledged that the poor Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had got a pocky <hi>Ozoena,</hi> the shame of which drove him him to despair, so that he not only dyed, but had lived like a true Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pionist. But let me not forget his pride and vanity, which was so eminent that having a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32868:17"/> contemptible name of which he was ashamed, he changed it from <hi>Johannes Bassus</hi> to <hi>Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Angelus Politianus;</hi> and this was a blessed example (was it not?) to vindicate a Celestial Horoscope?</p>
            <p>And certainly when Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended this blessed Church-man's Nativity for the glory of ♏, he was not aware how he betrayed his own ignorance; for before his Works printed at <hi>Basil</hi> 1553. you may find this Character of him: <hi>Erat distortis saepe moribus, ubi facie nequaquam ingenua &amp; libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali, ab enormi praesertim naso subluscoque oculo per absurdu, ingenio astuto, aculeato occulreque livido, cum aliena semper invideret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next is <hi>Argol</hi>'s celebrated Friend, whom <hi>Argol</hi> gives <hi>a very kind Character.</hi> Yes, and so he does ♏ too, <hi>Ptol. Parv.</hi> pag. 95. <hi>Scorpius facit bellicosos immanes, improbos, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, seditiosos, malorum morum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John Gheik</hi> is the next, and as our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor supposes, <hi>Neither Mr. L. nor any of his Tribe, will presume or esteem it a crime in him to have been Secretary of State.</hi> No not they, I dare engage, had not you very uncivilly laid Flattery and dissimulation to his charge, the <hi>ONLY stairs by which ALL Persons ascend to honour and preferment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have nothing to say against Doctor <hi>Fisk,</hi> only Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi> was his Pupil; and as he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32868:18"/> himself observes, <hi>Qualis Dominus talis Servis,</hi> Like Master like Man.</p>
            <p>Last of all comes our Author; and to his Nativity I shall onely accommodate an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorism of his own (and you know as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self observes all <hi>Aphorismes are indubitably true</hi>) as it is to be found in his Century at the end of his <hi>Coll. Gen. Aph.</hi> 87. ♂ in ☍ to the Ascendent, and ♄ in the same Aspect to the ☉, makes an absolute Knave or Treacher. But replyes <hi>John,</hi> ♄ is in □ to my ☉ if in any Aspect at all; for ☉ is separated nine deg. from him, and ♂ is out of Orbs. But let me ask him one question, why may not I allow as large Orbs as he? For he imputes a kind of necessity to the influence of the ☍ of ♂ and ♀ in <hi>Ssorza</hi>'s Nativity; who are as far asunder as ♂ from his Horoscope; and though a □ be not so bad as an ☍, yet it is next and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate after it. It may be as you say, that you never took the turn about Oaths of the times, yet you pretended to print Nativi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which the Law makes treason to calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late: but who were you, <hi>John,</hi> that should have Oaths imposed you? Alas! who could have found out a smyling Fellow, that (as your Annotator observes) fat cross-legged all day up in the Garret? But, saith <hi>John,</hi> I am a very surly Fellow sometimes, therefore provoke me not too far; <hi>Howbeit at this time
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32868:18"/> I will RƲLE my Stars, and FOLLOW Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter's gentle influence.</hi> Is not this a pleasant Rhetorical Cockscomb? Is is not a cunning way of ruling the Stars, by submitting to their influences? Why could he not with the Poet have said: <hi>I'le follow Fate, which doth too fast pursue.</hi> But it is impossible for our Author not to write non-sence, as it was in the dayes of yore, to patch a Suit without his Goose.</p>
            <p>I have now almost run through this migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Book, nothing remaining but a Postscript, an Advertisement, and his Almanack Rimes in defence of ♏. In his Postscript; I cannot but laugh at his <hi>Posthum'd legacy,</hi> which he shall leave the Sons of Art. I doubt his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is mistaken, and it should have been <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posthum'd,</hi> like Cleavland's <hi>Imposthum'd bubble of a wave,</hi> and it may be as much in it. But to leave trifling, saith <hi>John,</hi> let us come to his bouncing non-sence in rime, and when I read his Poetry I do not admire at our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb: <hi>as bad a Rimer as an Almanack maker:</hi> The gingles foisted, the wearish stuff, and contemptible fancy, are enough to make a man renounce Rime eternally. Yet is not this troublesome Fellow ashamed, to reprint these Rimes again in this Pamphlet, as a Corollary to his defence? In his <hi>February</hi>'s Observations you find these words:
<q>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:32868:19"/>
                  <l>The parts of Heaven, are like to Heaven alone,</l>
                  <l>As Heaven to God, that made it, who's but one.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which is as much as to say, the parts of Heaven, <hi>viz.</hi> the Signs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, are very much alike.</p>
            <q>
               <l>And how poor Scorpio being apart, should be</l>
               <l>Thus subject to surquedrious raillery,</l>
               <l>As to be stiled bad, the whole being good,</l>
               <l>Is not by me nor thousands understood.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Though it be not understood by thee, nor thousands as dull as thy self (if so many there be) yet <hi>John</hi> I would have you know, that Men of stronger intellects do compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it; and they will tell you, that those parts of Heaven, that are observed to be of evil influence in respect of us (though in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of themselves and us, they are essentially good) are very properly termed bad, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradistinction to those that are kind and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious: Thus is ♏ as properly stilled false, and treacherous, and ♄ and ♂ infortunes, as Hemlock, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> poysonous and destructive. <hi>For God saw all that he had made, and it was good.</hi>—But surquedrious!</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:32868:19"/>
               <l>The Goblia makes me start,</l>
               <l>I'th' name of Rabbi <hi>Abraham,</hi> what art?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Syriack,</hi> or <hi>Arabick,</hi> or <hi>Welch,</hi> what skilt?</l>
               <l>Some Conjurer translate.</l>
            </q>
            <p>For I declare I ken it not, but leave it for a pure piece of non-sence to the Author, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e what <hi>Rider</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> say to it.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Scorpio's a sign of brisk activity;</l>
               <l>And Men, born under the same, so be.—it.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Here our Poet thought he was praying for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he destruction of his Enemies; but for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime's sake was forced to leave out, <hi>It,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o to make it cry clink, wrote false Grammar.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Must action then be branded? whist my pen,</l>
               <l>We'l all be guided by dull sottish men.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I wish with all my heart, thy pen would once be so dull, or thou so sottish as to be whist, we should have the less noise with non-sence and tautology by far.</p>
            <q>
               <l>What Sign in all the twelve, yieldeth a man</l>
               <l>More good, more just, more learned than Scorpio?</l>
            </q>
            <p>These run, methinks, like his <hi>Epiphonema</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:32868:20"/> to his wit-ensuring Verses, to Phantast<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>al <hi>Heydon</hi> upon his Temple of Wisedom. <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>This I'le presage, your Book of Wisedom is</l>
               <l>A Guide, that leads to Nature's mysteries.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Now this was like the Conjurer of <hi>Brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court,</hi> and certainly Poet thou went'st to the Divel for this prediction; for did ever Man but thou undertake to presage a thing that is.</p>
            <p>Now for a piece of our Poets Religion, <hi>viz.</hi> A Trinity in unity; <hi>but Pictoribus atqu Poetis.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Ʋnder bless'd Scorpio happily was born,</l>
               <l>Our English Trismegist, the learned <hi>Brown.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>And why (thou Goose-cap) Trismegist O yes, he is the greatest Physician, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Philosopher, and the greatest what? Not Priest I hope: no, it shall be Scorpionist; much to the Doctor's reputation. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder favour, doth not the Physician come under the notion of a Philosopher? so that for ought I can see, the Doctor must be content, and hereafter write but Bismegist. But you shall hear the complement, our Poet passes upon this learned Person in another place, occasio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally speaking of him he tells (<hi>Doctr. of Nat.</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:32868:20"/> p. 130.) <hi>That although he wished we might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creat like trees, yet shortly after</hi> (though he is mistaken, for it was almost, or full seven years after) not being able to contain, <hi>he was so wrought upon by the power of Venus, that he was forced to betake to a comfortable importance.</hi> So that you see Mr. <hi>Gadbury</hi> making lechery the sole motive (or rather incentive) that this Gentleman had to marry, brings him under one branch of Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi>'s black charge before he is aware.</p>
            <p>But I am (and I believe, the Reader too) tired with the non-sence and contradictions of this Author, but had they not been dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played, he would have been so insolent and intolerable in his boasts, that he would not only have again confuted himself, but have been troublesome to his Neigbours, and have made such a noise and bluster about that part of Mankind, that cannot with judgment distinguish, and would have concluded that he had really obtained that victory, of which he will find he hath hitherto but dream'd.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>